Finding Aid for William Henry Phelps papers, 1872-1939
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Henry Phelps papers 1872-1939
Phelps, William Henry, 1872-1939.
2 linear feet
852038 Aa 2
Methodist Episcopal clergyman and editor of Michigan Christian Advocate. Correspondence relating to his editorial work and his interest in economic and labor problems, including the Flint, Michigan, Sit-Down Strike of 1937; also sermons, student paper, notebooks of classes at Albion College, and record of weddings performed in 1913 at the First Methodist Church of Battle Creek, Michigan; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. William H. Phelps (donor no. 873 ) and came to the library in 1938-1939.
The collection is open to research.
William Henry Phelps was born in Kalamazoo, Michigan on November 28, 1872. He graduated from Albion College (1894), Northwestern University (1895) and attended for two years the Boston University School of Theology. He began his career as a clergyman as pastor of a church in Martin, Mich. (1895-1897), followed by Coleman (1898) and Lansing (1899). In 1899, he was formally ordained into the ministry of the Methodist Episcopal Church. He then served in Grand Rapids (1899-1902), Manistee (1902-1904), Three Rivers (1904-1907), and Battle Creek (1907-1914). From 1914 to 1920, he served as district supervisor for the Lansing district of the Methodist Episcopal Church. Then from 1920 to his death in 1939, he was editor of the Michigan Christian Advocate. He died June 23, 1939.
The collection is arranged into three series: Correspondence, Sermons, and Other Materials. The great bulk of the collection is comprised of the manuscripts of his sermons in the period of 1895 to 1915.
Subjects:
Albion College.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Clergy--Michigan.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; First Methodist Church (Battle Creek, Mich.); Flint (Mich.); General Motors Corporation Sit-Down Strike, 1936-1937.; Journalists--Michigan.; Labor movement--Michigan.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Michigan Christian advocate.; Phelps, William Henry, 1872-1939.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Phelps, William Henry, 1872-1939.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Correspondence
  - Undated and 1872-1939, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Regarding questionnaire on the Flint Sit-Down Strike, 1937 (Box 1)
- Sermons
  - 1895-1897 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1911, 25 folders (Box 1)
  - 1912-1915 and undated, 17 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Manuscripts of stories sent to Phelps by M.H. Jack Wallis, 1934 and 1936 (Box 2)
  - Student paper, 1895 entitled, "The Relations of Queen Elizabeth to the Netherlands, 1558 to 1584" (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes and writings (Box 2)
  - Army papers and church appointments of Oliver H. Perry (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea concerning Edwin J. Phelps (Box 2)
  - Student notebook of chemistry lectures at Albion College, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Student notebook of botany lectures at Albion College, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Record book of weddings, and lists of Sunday School teachers, First Methodist Church, Battle Creek, Michigan, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)